howdy this is Jim rut and this is the
Jim rut show listeners have asked us to
provide pointers some of the resources
we talked about on the show we now have
links to books and articles referenced
in recent podcasts that are available on
our website
we also offer full transcripts go to Jim
rut show.com that's Jim ruts show com
this is another in our extra series of
koban 19 special short podcasts as usual
the audio quality won't be quite up to
our good standard but I hope the ideas
will more than make up for it
today's guest is Bonita Roy one of the
most interesting and innovative thinkers
writers talkers and doers on the planet
today she's been on our show before
she's been a longtime collaborator of
mine we don't always agree but that's
okay well I have tremendous respect for
where she's coming from the reason I
invited her on the show is more than
anybody else I know she has been
focusing on the possibilities on the
other side of this crisis and I just
loved a tremendous amount of what she's
written and one thing she wrote I think
yesterday day before really struck me
and I think sets the tone for how I'd
like our little brief discussion to go
let me read this is from Bonita crises
push people in one direction or the
other so we need to help each other move
from contraction cognitive shutdown and
moral dread to expansion collective
insight and moral courage by staying
together in deeper communion in
Parliament with the trouble we can
disclose this moment as screaming with
possibilities I just love that
so Bonita what are the possibilities oh
wow so you know from my vantage point
screaming with possibilities there's
there's just so many
of a wider breadth of quantity in the
depths of them let me just step back and
talk about what I was feeling when I
wrote that this notion of staying
together in Parliament with the trouble
what I'm referring to is that there are
many different interpretations of what's
going on there's many people are even
updating their interpretations as we go
along there's lots of conversations
displayed in many different ways and
what I want to suggest is that yes at
one level we have those conversations
but at the other level to expand our
perspective and see that all these
conversations are part of the same
movement I wrote once whether you
believe in coronavirus or not whether
you believe it from a biological and/or
epidemiological standpoint or whether
you think it's some I mean they're
radical conspiracy theories out there
what we can do is stay with what is
actually happening right the difference
between your interpretation of what is
happening and what is actually happening
I mean there's a lot going on and that's
what I mean by staying with the trouble
staying with how things are changing for
you staying with how today was different
than three weeks ago staying with the
choices that you're making today staying
with kind of this overwhelm of
information we really don't know we
don't have an exact grasp on the
statistics or the direction of what's
happening can we can we stay in this
open space of possibility and see it for
the possibilities that are arising so
this notion of staying with the trouble
means who is the first an invitation to
let go of your single interpretation and
just kind of like you know keep
advocating for that it get back to this
like the human condition of okay what's
our new human condition many of
are at home some of us are rejecting the
at home this and actually you know being
in deviant having deviant behavior so
whatever our behaviors that you've
adopted to see that they are part of the
same particular situation in this time
right so trying to just expand ourselves
out to that viewpoint I think is a very
valuable first for first step and then
in terms of the possibilities just
really be perceptive and aware and
observant insensitive to how things
change and what difference it makes I
was talking to a high school high school
students in Washington DC yesterday
about this it was very very fascinating
their comments so you know if you're not
going to work every day you know this
habits we get in we get our coffee we
get on the bus or the subway we go to
work we do the same things you know the
whole 9:00 to 5:00 if you're not doing
that then pay attention to how your life
has changed pay attention to maybe you
may be bored or anxious or looking at
why do i why have I been mindlessly
going to work you may find yourself
looking across the table at your
children playing in the corner or
fighting with each other and ask
yourself what do they actually do all
day when I'm not here or when they're in
school and and and what are the sweet
moments and what are not the sweet
moments when when we get you know we've
been forcefully removed from our habits
so we had an opportunity to look at
things from this new vantage point and
they may seem strange like it's like
it's strange that people live in you
know one of the things the students were
saying it's strange being in a house
because I'm in my room and we know we
separate ourselves everyone stays in
their own room and they thought well
that's kind of strange why why do we
lock ourselves in it into our own room
and so these these kind of noticing can
really start to generate curiosity and
inquiry into your own human condition
not only in terms of you as an
individual but you in your community and
enlarges you know social systems like
the economic and the supply chain and
all of this so the first invitation is
to not just get bored or not just be
anxious or not just the argumentative
about what it's happening but take
advantage of the fact that you have a
new vantage point can we can you be
sensitive to and observe from this new
place and see something for the first
time it reminds me of when I went to
college and I was very parochial and I
never even had a sleepover with a friend
when I was a kid and then I went away to
college and when I came back for
Thanksgiving I had a new vantage point
to look at my family dynamics you know
and I was like wow that's how we are so
this open this by itself opens a space
of possibility so that's what I mean by
staying in Parliament with the trouble a
parliament is called traditionally the
origins of the word as a parliament is
called on a temporary basis so people
can get together and reflect and review
on the situation that they face yeah I
like this very much I mean to my
perspective my interpretation of where
you're coming from is that if we hang
with our experiences and see and take
our experiences at this time seriously
it's going to give us a quite different
perspective than the everyday we're you
know for so many Americans they're sort
of numbed with routine activity you know
get up at six o'clock in the morning you
know do your morning cleanings and and
beautifying and rush off to work right
you know stop and pick up some pre-made
gloppy food from the grocery store on
the way home have a have a dinner help
the kids with their homework watch the
idiot TV watch
fallen to bed exhausted at 10:30 this is
a very different rhythm and we'll see
and we'll feel feel emotion ourselves
and we open ourselves up to that
experience will have parallax on the
life we used to live we very seldom have
yeah so and and and I think pointing
that out when I you know like I said
supporting people in that they can move
toward this more expansive curious
perspective I think we have to help each
other with that because it's not always
obvious you know because it is a big
change and we do get sucked into the to
the social media and the updates and
stuff like that so yeah helping each
other to have collective insight and
moral courage so moral courage I think
is important because when we're shaken
from our habits this this really
disrupts the the the organism you think
the psyche in and people can be
surprised that that happens it's
surprising to some people how much the
disruption of their routine makes a
difference even if you're sitting at
home in in and you look around and your
children are safe and your family
members are safe and you go to the store
and yeah you don't have all the choice
maybe that you used to but you have food
so if you think of the facts of the
matter then they seem to be really okay
and you might laugh at the fact of how
spoiled you were that you know there's
not so many varieties of the certain
pasta that you like or something but
when you notice that you're surprised or
you if you notice well there's only
these two types of pasta and you notice
what you the the feeling you get from
that the this is an important thing
because you haven't noticed
maybe the abundance or the overabundance
or the marketing or or you know when
when people come from other countries to
the US a lot of times they're just
surprised at what our grocery stores
look like but we can't actually see it
anymore right we can't actually see what
is the case because it's always the same
so give ourselves an opportunity to use
the difference to be able to reflect on
what was before and ask yourself you
know why should it be like before is
there some advantage point in turning
the tide in some respects you know one
of the things that people have trouble
with just in general is spaciousness you
know they're bored at home they don't
know what to do with themselves other
people have started to really take up
you know things that they've always
wanted to do and maybe they were just
simple things I read an article the
other day and I'm doing the same thing a
lot of people are making bread and
sewing you know these kind of ancient
archaic ways of hearth and home they
emerge in our in our being because these
this is fundamentally what we are as
humans before we stepped into like you
know the rat race and all these
manufactured systems we can attune to
our or pay attention to that how these
more fundamental hearth and home kind of
instincts arise this is happening for a
lot of people and not to trivialize it
not to just a lab oh I'm making bread or
something like that but to notice how it
feels and with that how that experience
arises in Nate Lee so those are some
some of them what I would say you know
if you start noticing them that's like
the world is screaming with new
possibilities and where are the
potentials in that I love it that's
great you know interesting you mentioned
bread who you know usually makes some
nice homemade bread once every couple of
weeks her and my daughter who were all
together our family and her husband and
we've been making bread continuously you
know rustic loaf pita bread you know
fine finer you know white bread
occasionally it's been quite interesting
in fact we joke ah this is the best
catered apocalypse ever we spend a lot
of time now take
care of each other taking care of our
food our you know our ceremonial
conviviality and all that in a way
that's richer than when we're all
dashing about our separate overloaded
days is interesting you also mentioned
the store shelves and you know this has
been been one of my pet peeves since
1994 when I saw the light and kind of
converted from a pure game a player to
something else is at one time went into
our local CVS pharmacy and counted 200
varieties of shampoo you know does the
world really need 200 varieties a
shampoo I don't think so and you know
another time another time I count at
their local martin's grocery store i
counted 77 varieties of barbecue sauce
Wow right
I wonder if this enforced simplification
of our lives will open the minds of at
least some people to say there's
something nutty and out of control about
the hyper abundance that money on money
return machine drives ourselves to every
niche exploits you know subdivided and
subdivided and subdivided again until
the last nickel is extracted from the
from the pockets of the consumer maybe
just maybe one of the possibilities on
the other side is experience doing
something different for an extended
period of time 4 6 8 12 weeks whatever
it turns out to be people maybe start to
be less programmed to the consumer
consumerist money on money machine thing
at least at least that's one of my hopes
yeah I mean we're hooked on the trivial
desires in this trivial pursuits in life
and disconnected from being resourceful
and and the true meaning making
practices of human community and family
but you know I've been writing this
essay for that's going to come out and
emerge and the question I have you know
I had to ask myself a question but why
is it for example that it's not why is
it that we will tend to just go back to
the rat race
this was very interesting to me I was on
some calls with people and people like
you and me and other people I know who
are resourceful have pantries filled
with natural health care and know how to
take care of I mean I have animals so we
do a lot of like you know basically you
know small level surgery and injections
on the farm and you know there's a
certain resourcefulness people like us
are not as affected by the this
situation than people who are in this
you know in the system in the global
economy let's say and the question is
why is it that the rat going back to the
rat race is so tempting you know why is
it that people just without
encouragement or without some of these
podcasts like you're doing why why isn't
it just obvious to them that they should
turn the tide and one of the things that
I realized and it was from reading an
article by Seema Mehra
it was an online magazine called the
conversation is that for most people for
many people there's not the option
between the rat race and this home and
hearth kind of thing we're talking about
but it's the rat between the rat race
and a dog-eat-dog world and this has to
do with you brought up this notion of
the you know the extractive economy and
what it is is in this article it made me
realize that the Simo mayor calls it
barbarism but that if you have a
centralized economy and you can you you
end up inviting people to the rat race
right so this kind of like extractive
economy but if that same economy becomes
distributed you have a dog-eat-dog world
because the economy is not set up to
serve people it's set up for to extract
value from exchange right and so this is
actually a smart choice that people are
making because they intuitively sense
that their options are between the rat
race and the dog-eat-dog world so it's
not just about expanding our imagination
from a centralized to a distributed
economy we have to change the function
of the economy to serve the needs and
protection of life and people and I
thought this was a big insight that I
had and and because I'm always kind of
skeptical of thinking that people are
not making the correct choices and they
seem like they're making the wrong
choices but I really truly believe now
that this is kind of the pickle that
most people are in it's between going
back to the rat race or what they see is
if all of a sudden the economy as we
know it gets distributed it will be a
dog-eat-dog world because it's primarily
rival risk
we understand economies and currencies
as rival risk we see them as extractive
and of value so we need to reimagine the
economy as servicing the needs of people
and in my article I'm writing about for
example if the food supply chain breaks
down let's say you know the people don't
have enough money to buy food that
truckers don't get paid to truck it the
migrant workers all go home right well
it's not like the earth stopped
producing food it's not like the Sun
stopped growing the food it's not like
any of the you know it's not like the
Sun started defying the laws of physics
none of that has changed it's just that
the mechanism of extractive value
exchange is broken down so what prevents
us from planting the seeds and
harvesting the food and getting in our
trucks and distributing what prevents us
from just continuing right and so it's
not very it's not a real far distance
between doing it the way we do now and
just continuing and in
you see the government is going to try
to inject money into the system so it'll
continue to do that but why do we need
that step why can't we define the design
for example essential goods and services
to work on a currency system that is
designed to protect its the flow of
essential goods and services to people
including healthcare and then once you
do that if you take that currency off of
the market then you can distribute it
then people will move toward it because
now it's no longer being being a local
kind of community inside an extractive
currency if now you can truly move from
the rat race to the to the community so
this I thought was a big big knowing or
something that really made a big
difference in the way that I understood
why it is that people go back to the rat
race so yeah so that's one thing and
another thing that was a big insight for
me you know just kind of modeling what
you can learn can you pay attention is
that a lot of people are saying oh this
crisis is showing us that were how
interconnected we are but I think I
would like to caution people I think
it's very important that you're not
experiencing interconnectedness because
the system is breaking down all you're
experiencing is that your depend upon
the system and there's a big difference
there and in fact the reason why the
food supply or the is fragile is because
you're connected to your food supplied
by the system so this is not a example
of deep interconnection it's a example
of unilateral dependency on a system
that's not that has a synchronous power
to you so if we were really interested
in deeper connection
and I think people when they get ahead
of that they really yearn for that then
for example we would be able to feed our
neighbors and go to the store and and
and have this kind of more generosity
this flow of goods essential goods and
services from person to person without
it having to be controlled centralized
and have the value extracted by by the
system so and we see this everywhere I
mean that why my mother has compromised
lungs every year she gets pneumonia we
wanted to buy at home oxygen a
respirator we asked you can't have one
without a prescription we asked her
doctor that she's known for years to
write her prescription and he can't
unless he can you know has a medical
record that she has pneumonia so these
are this is the way the system creates a
false asynchronous power relationship
people can learn how to do many of this
stuff at home and then you'll truly be
interconnected because you have
resources that your neighbors you can
share your neighbors and you can receive
from your neighbors also and we probably
giving the complexity of our lives need
some kind of currency for that but that
can be certainly off the wall street off
the financial instruments and be not
part of a debt economy and an extractive
value exchange so I think we're really
close to these things I'm writing this
article it has ten it's like a countdown
to what I call Regenesis has ten
interrelated principles that that many
of us have already worked out I'm not a
financial expert but I know that these
things are understood by people today
people like yourselves people in our
community all these ten areas are well
researched and can be handled by a
community people who've been working on
them and
long time and they support each other so
number two helps number three number
three helps number five get done in and
so what I'm hoping is this great this
notion of screaming with possibility is
that this is this is a moment in time
where people that are leading these
kinds of changes can be upregulated in
as leaders in our society that they can
convene community larger communities of
practices and that people can see that
it's a safe bet to move toward a world
that is that is better for all of us and
I really feel the possibility in that
and yeah and I'm trying as best as I can
to contribute yeah I'm very much looking
forward where you gonna publish that in
emerge that you say look look forward to
reading it let me give you a couple
responses reactions there
I like the distinction actually very
useful its opening my mind a little bit
because we do our money economy is
extraordinarily inter woven at very long
distances and driven by again the
economics of money on money returning
example I give is and if it turns out
you that you know Walmart can get a
t-shirt for five cents less that's made
in Bangladesh by semi slave labor than
made in a good job a good wage paying
job in South Carolina the money on money
return signal says do it even though it
devastates the town in South Carolina
and empowers kind of capitalist
exploiters in Bangladesh and why should
that why should cotton go from Texas to
Bangladesh and back again burning fossil
fuels all the while because it's what is
the reason is the driver is our money on
money return anyway this the economy is
this unbelievably complicated network a
very long distance exchanges aimed at
you know financial optimization in fact
I saw
I'm say people say the internet was the
greatest invention of the 20th century
maybe it was the shipping container that
cut the cost of long-distance you know
transcontinental intercontinental
commerce by a factor of five cheaper
than it used to be but then so we put
that in one bag this this monster string
network beast optimized of huge
complexity in optimizing money terms but
not optimized in terms of what's good
for communities and for the world and on
the other side as you point out as is
something I had not thought of quite in
these ways before our relationship with
that beast is a peculiar one right it's
not a rich relationship it's not a
strong link really do we have any
emotional affinity to the we buy at
Walmart I don't write and we just take
it as a given there's no human
humaneness to it there's no deep
reciprocity
I don't expect Walmart to help me out
when I'm out of work on the other hand
if I'm trading locally with people I
know and I'm out of work you know
frankly it's very reasonable for them to
continue to front me eggs and milk for a
few months right and I'll help them by
chopping their firewood this winter and
I do think this is the biggest
possibility then and unfortunately the
alternative really isn't ready I wish it
was I wish we were further along and
building what we sometimes call the game
be world where things are much more
local more modular more peer-to-peer
more self-organizing more Network
centric but but we're not we're building
some of the ideas and a very few of the
tools but I do think that this
possibility has opened a bunch of eyes
right for the first time in a long time
people are having to make consequential
decisions for themselves and maybe ten
times as many people are now ready to
hear the message and start getting to
work to build out this alternative world
that you alluded to with a you know a
financial signaling mechanism that
builds community not optimized for
economic short-term return and you know
I'm really hoping that
the number of ears that here has grown
by a factor of 10 at least due to this
process so that we could start the real
work or being ready for the next one
because I think those of us who follow
this stuff closely know this is not the
last big shock to the status quo
far from it in fact as apocalypses go
this one's pretty but I'm in as far as I
can tell we should we should not expect
basic infrastructure to stop working
like electricity and water and sewage
and probably not food we get a further
simplification in our food chain but at
least in the United States I see no
reason that the grocery stores won't
stay open but the next one could be a
lot worse and I think the you know
message I'd like to get out to the world
it's really time to get serious about
building this alternative building this
game B so that when the next one occurs
there really will be a place to go to
away from the rat race and to build this
closer to the earth closer to our
neighbors strong links rest reciprocity
based civilization that isn't driven by
can I squeeze the last nickel out of
every dollar yep yeah I mean I think
that from two different perspectives one
is I think we're a long way from the
whole kit and kaboodle to change but I
think that if we change our design
approach I see that this is much more
doable if we move to parallel systems
you know so if we take essential goods
and services off of the main currency I
don't see that as being a big deal I and
actually I mean we don't want to get
into the details here because I actually
also disagree that the only thing that's
driving these incredibly complex supply
chains are efficiencies
I think the efficiencies are
manufactured the the the dry
efficiencies are manufactured by the
structure or the financial system itself
and so yes if you're running a company
you're you're forced to enter this game
of efficiency
that's because the subsidies in the
larger financial system make these long
supply chains more efficient than short
supply chains
it's a manufactured imperative for
efficiency at the corporate level this
is this is another big thing that I
think it insight that people need to
know so and the reason why that is that
the financial system is structured that
way is because if you're you're growing
chickens in the US and you're shipping
them to China and then they're coming
back what happens is the financial
global financial system you know GDP in
the u.s. is something like 30 percent of
just finance on Finance now and it's
because the more transactions that
happen the longer and more complex the
supply chain the more points at which
you can extract value so the system
needs these long convoluted complex
supply chains in order to extract value
so they subsidize the system subsidizes
movements in such a way so there are
more more changes of hand to get the
chicken back to your plate and then
those subsidies make it look like it's
more efficient to do that but that's
because it's a structure inefficiency
this is what I truly believe I think
that it's a big part of how we get from
here to there faster I think that the
the illusion that long supply chains are
more efficient that we actually pull
that off is a big delusion that is got
us stuck I love talk to you about that
someday yep and that's a great
distinction because it is efficient in
the measure of money on money return but
only in that dimension and as this whole
thing is showing us its efficiency
that's traded off against resiliency and
robustness there's nobody
nothing in the money on money return
that says we should have had a twenty
billion faced math fly for the
inevitable pandemic the efficient supply
chains of Johnson and Johnson do not
send that signal right somebody else
some social system has to send that
signal and that's where we're broken
well banette I've we've kind of read I
think let's leave it at that that's
probably this everyone takes a lot this
has been a wonderful this was every bit
as good as I thought and I had high
expectations as I always do when I
interact with Bonito one of the smartest
say biasts biggest artists people I know
so thank you for being on the show one
day we'll meet jimin will give us each
other a good post coronavirus hug we're
very good thank you
[Music]
production services and audio editing by
Jared Jane's consulting music by Tom
Muller at modern space music com
[Music]